As a boy in Lima,
عندما كنتُ صبياً في ليما،
my grandfather told me a legend
حدّثني جدي عن أسطورة
of the Spanish conquest of Peru.
بشأن الغزو الإسباني لبيرو.
Atahualpa, emperor of the Inca, had been captured and killed.
تم أسر وقتل قيصر الإنكا "أتاوالبا".
Pizarro and his conquistadors had grown rich,
وإغتنى بيزارو ومن معه من الغزاة.
and tales of their conquest and glory had reached Spain
ووصلت حكايات ومجد غزوهم إلى إسبانيا
and was bringing new waves of Spaniards, hungry for gold and glory.
وجلبت معها أفواجا من سكان إسبانيا الأصليين المتعطشين التواقين للذهب والمجد.
They would go into towns and ask the Inca,
كانوا يذهبون للمدن ويسألون سكان الإنكا،
"Where's another civilization we can conquer? Where's more gold?"
"أين توجد حضارة أخرى يمكننا غزوها؟ أين يوجد المزيد من الذهب؟"
And the Inca, out of vengeance, told them,
وأخبرهم سكان الإنكا كنوعٍ من الإنتقام.
"Go to the Amazon.
"إذهبوا إلى منطقة الأمازون.
You'll find all the gold you want there.
ستجدون هناك كل الذهب الذي تريدون.
In fact, there is a city called Paititi -- El Dorado in Spanish --
هناك بالفعل مدينة تُدعى "Paititi"-- بمعنى الذهب في اللغة الإسبانية --
made entirely of gold."
مصنوعة بالكامل من الذهب."
The Spanish set off into the jungle,
فانطلق الإسبان إلى الأدغال،
but the few that return come back with stories,
ولكن عاد القليل منهم ومعهم قصص وحكايات،
stories of powerful shamans,
قصص عن قوة الشامان،
of warriors with poisoned arrows,
عن محاربين بالسهام المسمومة،
of trees so tall they blotted out the sun,
للأشجار العالية التي تصل للشمس،
spiders that ate birds, snakes that swallowed men whole
للعناكب التي أكلت الطيور، والأفاعي التي إبتلعت الرجال بالكامل
and a river that boiled.
والنهر الذي يغلي.
All this became a childhood memory.
أصبح كل هذا ذكريات الطفولة.
And years passed.
ومرت السنوات.
I'm working on my PhD at SMU,
وأعمل الآن على درجة الدكتوراه في جامعة SMU في دالاس،
trying to understand Peru's geothermal energy potential,
محاولاً فهم الطاقة الحرارية الارضية في بيرو،
when I remember this legend,
وعندها تذكرت هذه الأسطورة،
and I began asking that question.
وبدأت بطرح هذا السؤال.
Could the boiling river exist?
هل يوجد النهر الذي يغلي؟
I asked colleagues from universities,
سألتُ الزملاء من الجامعات،
the government,
والحكومة،
oil, gas and mining companies,
وشركات النفط والغاز والتعدين،
and the answer was a unanimous no.
وكان الجواب "لا" بالإجماع.
And this makes sense.
وهذا الأمر له معنى.
You see, boiling rivers do exist in the world,
أتعلمون توجد الأنهار التي تغلي في العالم،
but they're generally associated with volcanoes.
ولكن التي يُصاحبها البراكين عموماً.
You need a powerful heat source
أنتم بحاجة إلى مصدر حراري قوي
to produce such a large geothermal manifestation.
لإنتاج مثل هذه الكمية الهائلة من الطاقة الحرارية الأرضية الواضحة.
And as you can see from the red dots here, which are volcanoes,
وكما ترون من هذه النقاط الحمراء التي هي براكين،
we don't have volcanoes in the Amazon,
ليس لدينا البراكين في منطقة الأمازون،
nor in most of Peru.
ولا في معظم أنحاء بيرو.
So it follows: We should not expect to see a boiling river.
وبالتالي، ينبغي علينا أن لا نتوقع روية نهرٌ يغلي.
Telling this same story at a family dinner,
قلتُ نفس هذه القصة في عشاءٍ عائلي،
my aunt tells me,
تقول عمتي/خالتي لي،
"But no, Andrés, I've been there. I've swum in that river."
"لكن لا أندريس، كنتُ هناك، ولقد سبحتُ في ذلك النهر."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Then my uncle jumps in.
ثم ينهضُ عمي/خالي ويقول:
"No, Andrés, she's not kidding.
"لا أندريس، إنها لا تمزح،
You see, you can only swim in it after a very heavy rain,
أترى، يمكنك السباحة في النهر بعد هطول الأمطار الغزيرة جداً،
and it's protected by a powerful shaman.
وهو محميٌ من قبل قوة الشامان،
Your aunt, she's friends with his wife."
إن عمتك/خالتك صديقة لزوجته."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"¿Cómo?" ["Huh?"]
كيف؟ [هاه؟]
You know, despite all my scientific skepticism,
أتعلمون، على الرغم من كل شكوكي العلمية،
I found myself hiking into the jungle, guided by my aunt,
وجدتُ نفسي أمشي لمسافات طويلة في الغابات، بمساعدة عمتي/خالتي،
over 700 kilometers away from the nearest volcanic center,
على بعد 700 كيلومتر من أقرب مركز بركاني،
and well, honestly, mentally preparing myself
وصراحةً، حضّرتُ نفسي ذهنياً بشكل جيد
to behold the legendary "warm stream of the Amazon."
لرصد الأسطورة "مجرى التيار الدافىء لمنطقة الأمازون."
But then ...
ولكن لاحقاً ...
I heard something,
سمعتُ شيئاً،
a low surge
حركة موجة تصاعدية منخفضة
that got louder and louder
والتي أصبحت أعلى وأعلى حدّة
as we came closer.
كلما اقتربنا.
It sounded like ocean waves constantly crashing,
بدت كأمواج المحيط التي تتلاطم بإستمرار،
and as we got closer, I saw smoke, vapor, coming up through the trees.
وأصبحنا أكثر قرباً، ورأيت الدخان والبخار يخرجُ من خلال الأشجار.
And then, I saw this.
وبعد ذلك، رأيت هذا.
I immediately grabbed for my thermometer,
وأمسكتُ على الفور ميزان الحرارة،
and the average temperatures in the river
ومتوسط درجة الحرارة في النهر
were 86 degrees C.
كانت 86 درجة مئوية.
This is not quite the 100-degree C boiling
إنها ليست درجة الغليان، 100 درجة مئوية،
but definitely close enough.
ولكنها في الواقع قريبة بما فيه الكفاية.
The river flowed hot and fast.
تدفق النهر على نحوٍ حار وسريع.
I followed it upriver and was led by, actually, the shaman's apprentice
وتتبعتها إلى أعلى النهر بقيادة متدرب الشامان في الواقع
to the most sacred site on the river.
إلى أكثر مكان مقدّس على النهر.
And this is what's bizarre --
وهذا هو الغريب --
It starts off as a cold stream.
إنه يندفعُ كتيار بارد.
And here, at this site,
وهنا عند هذا الموقع،
is the home of the Yacumama,
بيت ياكوماما "Yacumama"،
mother of the waters, a giant serpent spirit
أم الماء وكل مخلوقات الماء، روح الأفعى العملاقة
who births hot and cold water.
التي تلدُ الماء البارد والحار.
And here we find a hot spring,
وجدنا هنا ينبوع حاراً،
mixing with cold stream water underneath her protective motherly jaws
يختلطُ بتيار مائي بارد تحت حماية فكي الأمومة "الأفعى"
and thus bringing their legends to life.
وبالتالي تخرج اساطير "الشامان" إلى الحياة.
The next morning, I woke up and --
إستيقظتُ في صباح اليوم التالي ---
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I asked for tea.
وسألتُ عن الشاي.
I was handed a mug, a tea bag
وتسلمتُ في يدي قدحاً وكيساً من الشاي
and, well, pointed towards the river.
وحسناً، أشاروا لي نحو النهر.
To my surprise, the water was clean and had a pleasant taste,
لدهشتي، كانت المياه نظيفة وذات طعم لطيف،
which is a little weird for geothermal systems.
غريبة قليلاً عن أنظمة الطاقة الحرارية الأرضية.
What was amazing
ما كان مذهلاً
is that the locals had always known about this place,
هو أن السكان المحليين يعرفون عن هذا المكان،
and that I was by no means the first outsider to see it.
وكنتُ بأي حالٍ من الأحوال أول غريب يراه.
It was just part of their everyday life.
كان مجرد جزء لا يتجزأ من حياتهم اليومية.
They drink its water.
إنهم يشربون الماء منه،
They take in its vapor.
إنهم يستعملون بخاره،
They cook with it,
وإنهم يطهون طعامهم به،
clean with it,
وينظفون به،
even make their medicines with it.
حتى أنهم يصنعون أدويتهم بإستخدامه.
I met the shaman,
قابلتُ الشامان،
and he seemed like an extension of the river and his jungle.
وبدا وكأنه إمتداد للنهر والأدغال.
He asked for my intentions
سألني عن أهدافي ونواياي
and listened carefully.
واستمع لي بإنتباه وعناية.
Then, to my tremendous relief --
ومن ثم يا لراحتي العظيمة --
I was freaking out, to be honest with you --
لأكون صريحاً معكم، كنتُ مفزوعاً --
a smile began to snake across his face, and he just laughed.
وبدأت ترتسم على وجهه إبتسامة، وضحك فقط،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I had received the shaman's blessing to study the river,
تلقيتُ بركة الشامان لدراسة النهر،
on the condition that after I take the water samples
على شرط أنه وبعد أخذي عينات الماء
and analyze them in my lab,
وتحليلها في مختبري،
wherever I was in the world,
أينما كنتُ في العالم،
that I pour the waters back into the ground
عليّ سكب الماء في الأرض مرة أخرى
so that, as the shaman said,
وبذلك وكما قال الشامان،
the waters could find their way back home.
يُمكن للمياه أن تجد طريق العودة لبيتها "النهر".
I've been back every year since that first visit in 2011,
ومنذُ تلك الزيارة الأولى عام 2011، فإنني أعود إلى المكان كل عام،
and the fieldwork has been exhilarating,
وأصبح العمل الميداني مثيراً مبهجاً،
demanding and at times dangerous.
وملحاً وأحياناً محفوفاً بالمخاطر.
One story was even featured in National Geographic Magazine.
حتى ظهرت قصة في مجلة "ناشونال جيوغرافيك".
I was trapped on a small rock about the size of a sheet of paper
لقد حوصرتُ على صخرة صغيرة حوالي حجم الورقة
in sandals and board shorts,
في صندل وسروال واسع،
in between an 80 degree C river
في النهر بدرجة حرارة 80 درجة مئوية
and a hot spring that, well, looked like this, close to boiling.
وبدا الينبوع الحار قريبا من درجة الغليان.
And on top of that, it was Amazon rain forest.
وعلاوة على ذلك، كانت غابات الأمازون كثيرة الأمطار.
Pshh, pouring rain, couldn't see a thing.
تنساب الأمطار بكثرة ولا أرى شيئاً.
The temperature differential made it all white. It was a whiteout.
وجعل الفرق في درجات الحرارة كل شيء أبيض، كان بياضاً.
Intense.
شديداً.
Now, after years of work,
حالياً، وبعد سنوات من العمل،
I'll soon be submitting my geophysical and geochemical studies for publication.
سأقدم قريباً دراساتي الجيوفيزيائية والجيوكيميائية للنشر.
And I'd like to share, today, with all of you here, on the TED stage,
وأرغبُ اليوم مشاركتكم جميعاً، ومن منصة TED،
for the first time, some of these discoveries.
بعض هذه الإكتشافات ولأول مرة.
Well, first off, it's not a legend.
حسناً، قبل كل شيء، ليس الأمر أسطورة.
Surprise!
مفاجأة!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When I first started the research,
عندما بدأتُ البحث لأول مرة،
the satellite imagery was too low-resolution to be meaningful.
كانت تفاصيل صور القمر الإصطناعي ذات دقة منخفضة لتكون ذات مغزي.
There were just no good maps.
لم يكن هناك خرائط جيدة.
Thanks to the support of the Google Earth team,
وبضل دعم فريق جوجل إيرث (برنامج خرائطي وجغرافي)،
I now have this.
لدي هذا الآن.
Not only that, the indigenous name of the river, Shanay-timpishka,
ليس هذا فحسب، فالإسم المحلي للنهر هو "Shanay-timpishka"
"boiled with the heat of the sun,"
"يغلي مع حرارة الشمس،"
indicating that I'm not the first to wonder why the river boils,
مبيناً أنني لستُ أول من تساءل لماذا يغلي النهر،
and showing that humanity has always sought to explain
وموضحاً أن البشرية سعت دائماً لشرح
the world around us.
العالم من حولنا.
So why does the river boil?
لذا، فلماذا النهر يغلي؟
(Bubbling sounds)
(أصوات فقاقيع المياه)
It actually took me three years to get that footage.
إستغرق الأمرمني ثلاث سنوات لتصوير تلك اللقطة.
Fault-fed hot springs.
التصدعات تغذي الينابيع الحارة.
As we have hot blood running through our veins and arteries,
وكما لدينا الدم الحار يجري من خلال الأوردة والشرايين،
so, too, the earth has hot water running through its cracks and faults.
هكذا الأرض أيضاً لديها المياه الحارة التي تمرُ عبر الشقوق والتصدعات،
Where these arteries come to the surface, these earth arteries,
حيثُ تأتي هذه الشرايين للسطح، شرايين الأرض هذه،
we'll get geothermal manifestations:
سنحصل على مظاهر الطاقة الحرارية الأرضية:
fumaroles, hot springs and in our case, the boiling river.
فالمنافذ البركانية والينابيع الحارة، وفي حالتنا النهر الذي يغلي.
What's truly incredible, though, is the scale of this place.
مع ذلك فالمدهشُ حقاً هو حجم هذا المكان.
Next time you cross the road, think about this.
عندما تعبرُ الطريق في المرة القادمة، فكر في هذا.
The river flows wider than a two-lane road
يتدفق النهرعلى نحو أوسع من طريقٍ ذو مسارين
along most of its path.
على طول معظم مساره.
It flows hot for 6.24 kilometers.
يتدفق حاراً على طول 6.24 كيلومتر.
Truly impressive.
إنه حقا مثيرٌ للإعجاب .
There are thermal pools larger than this TED stage,
هناك حمامات حرارية أكثر من مسرح TED هذا،
and that waterfall that you see there
وتلك شلالات الماء التي تراها هناك
is six meters tall --
بطول ستة أمتار --
and all with near-boiling water.
وجميعها مياه قريبة من درجة الغليان.
We mapped the temperatures along the river,
رسمنا خريطة درجات الحرارة على طول النهر،
and this was by far the most demanding part of the fieldwork.
وكان ذلك -وإلى حدٍ بعيد- الجزء الاكثر إلحاحاً في العمل الميداني.
And the results were just awesome.
وكانت النتائج مذهلة.
Sorry -- the geoscientist in me coming out.
آسف - أنا أتحدث الآن كعالم جيولوجي.
And it showed this amazing trend.
وأظهرت هذا الإتجاه المذهل.
You see, the river starts off cold.
أترون، يتدفق النهر في البداية بارداً
It then heats up, cools back down, heats up, cools back down,
وثم يسخن، وتنخفض سخونته، ثم يسخن، ويبرد مرة أخرى،
heats up again, and then has this beautiful decay curve
ويسخن مرة أخرى، وثم يصبح لديه منحنى التضاول الجميل هذا
until it smashes into this cold river.
حتى يسقط في هذا النهر البارد.
Now, I understand not all of you are geothermal scientists,
أدركُ الآن ليس جميعكم علماء جيولوجيا حرارية،
so to put it in more everyday terms:
لذلك، وللتعبير عنها بمصطلحات يومية:
Everyone loves coffee.
الجميع فيكم يحب القهوة.
Yes? Good.
نعم؟ جيد.
Your regular cup of coffee, 54 degrees C,
درجة حرارة قدح قهوتكم العادي هي 54 مْ،
an extra-hot one, well, 60.
والقدح الأكثر سخونة 60 مْ.
So, put in coffee shop terms,
لذلك، حسب مصطلحات المقهى،
the boiling river plots like this.
يشبه النهر الذي يغلي هذا.
There you have your hot coffee.
لديك في المقهى قهوتك الساخنة.
Here you have your extra-hot coffee,
وهنا لديك قهوتك الأكثر سخونة.
and you can see that there's a bit point there
ويمكن أن ترى أن هناك نقطة صغيرة
where the river is still hotter than even the extra-hot coffee.
حيث ما زال النهر أكثر سخونة حتى من القهوة الأكثر سخونة.
And these are average water temperatures.
وهذه هي معدل درجات حرارة المياه.
We took these in the dry season to ensure the purest geothermal temperatures.
سجلنا درجات الحرارة هذه في موسم الجفاف لضمان نقاوة الدرجات الحرارية الأرضية
But there's a magic number here that's not being shown,
لكن هناك رقم سحري والذي لم يظهر،
and that number is 47 degrees C,
وهذا الرقم هو 47 درجة مئوية،
because that's where things start to hurt,
حيثُ هنا تبدأ الأشياء بالإيذاء،
and I know this from very personal experience.
وأعرف ذلك تماماً من تجربتي الشخصية.
Above that temperature, you don't want to get in that water.
لا تريدُ أن تغطس في الماء فوق تلك الدرجة.
You need to be careful.
عليك أن تكون حذراً.
It can be deadly.
يمكنُ أن تكون قاتلة.
I've seen all sorts of animals fall in,
رأيتُ جميع أنواع الحيوانات تقع فيها،
and what's shocking to me, is the process is pretty much the same.
وما كان مُروعاً بالنسبة لي هو أن العملية هي نفسها إلى حدٍ كبير.
So they fall in and the first thing to go are the eyes.
يقعون فيها وأول شيء يتغيرهو العيون.
Eyes, apparently, cook very quickly. They turn this milky-white color.
يبدو أن العينين تُطهى بسرعة، وتتحولان إلى لون أبيض حليبي.
The stream is carrying them.
ويحملهم التيار.
They're trying to swim out, but their meat is cooking on the bone
يحاولون السباحة للخروج، لكن تُطهى لحومها على عظامها
because it's so hot.
لأن المياه حارة جدًا.
So they're losing power, losing power,
وبذلك يفقدون مقاومتهم ويفقدون قوتهم،
until finally they get to a point where hot water goes into their mouths
حتى وصولهم في النهاية إلى النقطة حيثُ تدخلُ المياه الحارة إلى أفهواهم
and they cook from the inside out.
لتطهو أجسامهم من الداخل إلى الخارج.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A bit sadistic, aren't we?
سادية بعض الشيء، ألسنا كذلك؟
Jeez.
هذا مفاجئ ومرعب حقاً.
Leave them marinating for a little longer.
تركهم منغمسين لفترة أطول قليلاً.
What's, again, amazing are these temperatures.
ما هو مدهش مرةً أخرى هي درجات الحرارة هذه.
They're similar to things that I've seen on volcanoes all over the world
إنها تماثلُ الأشياء التي رأيتها بخصوص البراكين في جميع أنحاء العالم
and even super-volcanoes like Yellowstone.
وحتى أعلى وأفظع البراكين مثل بركان يلوستون في أمريكا.
But here's the thing:
ولكن هناك شيء:
the data is showing that the boiling river exists
تُظهر البيانات وجود النهر الذي يغلي
independent of volcanism.
مستقلاً عن النشاط البركاني.
It's neither magmatic or volcanic in origin,
فهو في الأصل لا منصهر ولا بركاني،
and again, over 700 kilometers away from the nearest volcanic center.
ومرةً أخرى، من على بعد 700 كيلومتر من أقرب مركز بركاني.
How can a boiling river exist like this?
كيف يوجد نهر يغلي مثل هذا؟
I've asked geothermal experts and volcanologists for years,
سألتُ خبراء الطاقة الحرارية الجوفية وعلماء دراسة البراكين لسنوات،
and I'm still unable to find another non-volcanic geothermal system
وما زلتُ غير قادر على إيجاد نظام آخر للطاقة الحرارية الأرضية غير البركانية
of this magnitude.
بهذا الحجم.
It's unique.
إنه فريد من نوعه.
It's special on a global scale.
إنه خاص على المستوى العالمي.
So, still -- how does it work?
ومع ذلك، لا زال السؤال-- كيف يعمل؟
Where do we get this heat?
أين نحصل على هذه الحرارة؟
There's still more research to be done
ما زالت هناك بحوث يجب القيام بها
to better constrain the problem and better understand the system,
لحصر المشكلة بطريقة أفضل، وفهم أفضل للنظام.
but from what the data is telling us now,
لكن ما تُخبرنا به البيانات حالياً،
it looks to be the result of a large hydrothermal system.
يبدو كنتيجة نظام مائي حراري.
Basically, it works like this:
إنه في الأساس يعمل هكذا:
So, the deeper you go into the earth, the hotter it gets.
كلما اتجهت نحو أعماق الأرض، تصبح الأرض أسخن.
We refer to this as the geothermal gradient.
ونشيرُ لهذا كمدرج الحرارة الأرضية.
The waters could be coming from as far away as glaciers in the Andes,
يمكن أن تأتي المياه من مناطق بعيدة مثل الأنهار الجليدية في جبال الأنديز،
then seeping down deep into the earth
ومن ثم تتسرب إلى اسفل في أعماق الأرض
and coming out to form the boiling river
وتخرجُ لتشّكل النهر الذي يغلي
after getting heated up from the geothermal gradient,
بعد أن تحصل على الحرارة من مدرج الحرارة الأرضية،
all due to this unique geologic setting.
كل ذلك بسبب هذا النظام الجيولوجي النادر.
Now, we found that in and around the river --
حالياً، وجدنا أن في النهر وحوله --
this is working with colleagues
هذا هو العمل مع الزملاء
from National Geographic, Dr. Spencer Wells,
من ناشونال جيوغرافيك، د. سبنسر ويلز،
and Dr. Jon Eisen from UC Davis --
ود. جون إيسن من جامعة كاليفورنيا - دافيس -
we genetically sequenced the extremophile lifeforms
نحنُ سجلنا وراثياً أشكال الحياة لأُلفاء الظروف القاسية
living in and around the river, and have found new lifeforms,
التي تعيش في النهر وحوله، ووجدنا أشكال حياة جديدة،
unique species living in the boiling river.
كائنات حية نادرة تعيشُ في النهر الذي يغلي.
But again, despite all of these studies, all of these discoveries and the legends,
ولكن مرةً أخرى، وعلى الرغم من جميع الدراسات، وكل هذه الإكتشافات والأساطير،
a question remains:
يبقى سؤال:
What is the significance of the boiling river?
ما هي أهمية النهر الذي يغلي؟
of this stationary cloud
ما هي أهمية هذه السحابة الثابتة
that always hovers over this patch of jungle?
التي تحومُ دائماً فوق هذه البقعة من الأدغال؟
And what is the significance
وما هي أهمية
of a detail in a childhood legend?
التفاصيل في اسطورة الطفولة؟
To the shaman and his community, it's a sacred site.
بالنسبة للشامان ومجتمعه، فإنها مكان مقدس.
To me, as a geoscientist,
وبالنسبة لي كعالم جيولوجي،
it's a unique geothermal phenomenon.
فهي ظاهرة الطاقة الحرارية الأرضية الفريدة من نوعها.
But to the illegal loggers and cattle farmers,
ولكن بالنسبة لقاطعي الأشجار بشكل غير قانوني وللمزارعين رعاة الماشية،
it's just another resource to exploit.
فهي مجرد مصدر آخر للنفع.
And to the Peruvian government, it's just another stretch
وبالنسبة لحكومة بيرو، فإنها مجرد مساحة أخرى
of unprotected land ready for development.
من الأراضي غير المحمية الجاهزة للتحسين.
My goal is to ensure that whoever controls this land
هدفي هو ضمان أن أياً كان من يسيطرُ على هذه الأرض
understands the boiling river's uniqueness and significance.
عليه فهم أهمية وتفرد النهر الذي يغلي.
Because that's the question,
لأنّ هذا هو السؤال،
one of significance.
سؤال الأهمية.
And the thing there is,
والمسألة هناك،
we define significance.
نحنُ مَنْ نُحدد الأهمية.
It's us. We have that power.
إنها نحنُ. لدينا تلك السلطة.
We are the ones who draw that line
نحنُ الذين نرسمُ الحد الفاصل
between the sacred and the trivial.
بين المقدّس والتافه.
And in this age,
وفي هذا العصر،
where everything seems mapped, measured and studied,
حيث يبدو كل شيء مرسوماً ومُقاساً ومدروساً.
in this age of information,
في عصر المعلومات هذا،
I remind you all that discoveries are not just made
أُذكركم جميعاً ليست كل الإكتشافات تم صنعها
in the black void of the unknown
من الفراغ الأسود للمجهول
but in the white noise of overwhelming data.
ولكن من الضجيج الأبيض للبيانات المكثفة العظيمة.
There remains so much to explore.
لا يزال هناك الكثير لإستكشافه.
We live in an incredible world.
نحن نعيشُ في عالمٍ بديع رائع.
So go out.
لذلك، أخرجوا.
Be curious.
كونوا فضوليين.
Because we do live in a world
لأننا نعيشُ في عالمٍ
where shamans still sing to the spirits of the jungle,
حيث ما زال الشامان ينشدون لأرواح الأدغال،
where rivers do boil
حيثما تغلي الأنهار.
and where legends do come to life.
حيث الأساطير تخرج للحياة.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)